<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the protestation of Monseigneur the Mareschal d'Anuille</title>
            <author>Montmorency, Henri, duc de, 1534-1614.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1575</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07659</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18051.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4789</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23891228</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23891228</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26953</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07659)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26953)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1837:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the protestation of Monseigneur the Mareschal d'Anuille</title>
                  <author>Montmorency, Henri, duc de, 1534-1614.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[15] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1575]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Text begins: We Henrie of Monmorency, Lorde of Danuille mareschal of Fraunce, gouerner and lieutenant general for the King, in the countrey of Languedoc ...</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Wars of the Huguenots, 1562-1598.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26953:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 63 -->
            <head>A DECLARA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION OF THE PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TESTATION OF MON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeigneur the Mareſchal d'Anuille.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E Henrie of Monmorency, Lorde of Danuille Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal of Fraunce, Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and Lieutenaunt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral for the King, in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of Languedoc, Deſiring that euerie man may knowe and vnderſtande, that the onelie dutie and fidelitie that we haue borne to the ſeruice of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and to the profit and quiet of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes and of his Realme, hath moued vs to entre into armes againſt the diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and oppreſſers thereof. For this cauſe do declare to all Kinges, Princes, and Pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tates of Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dome, frendes confederates, and allyes of his Crowne, &amp; to all his Maieſties faithfull ſubiectes of what eſtate, qualitie, or condicion ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they be, that hauing perceiued theſe
<pb facs="tcp:26953:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 64 -->
fourtene yere paſt, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhortly after the deceſſe of the late King Henrie of good memorie, how this poore and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate Realme hath in all ſortes been af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted and oppreſſed with ciuile warres, grounded vpon the pretenſe and contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie of Religion, and how vnder this pretenſe hath folowed the totall ruine of the more parte of the good Townes that haue been ſpoiled and ſacked, and ſome of them ofter than once, as the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſordred and vnſatiable paſſion of ſuche as were the authors of all theſe miſeries hath had will to entrepriſe and put in execution: how the edictes and ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces made at the generall aſſemblie of the Eſtates at Orleans, and ſince that time ſo oft renewed, as well for the pacifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Realme, as for the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce thereof, haue in all thinges ben periurouſly broken: how impunitie of murders, ſlaughters, poyſonninges, ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinges of tumoltes of the people, defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges of women, and maides, burnin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ſackinges, and other haynous doynges, generally haue been, and be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated in this Realme, by thoſe that
<pb facs="tcp:26953:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 64 -->
ought to haue ſtayed the ſame, euen ſo farre as that thei haue ſuffred that cruel barbarous, and vnnatural murder of the more part of the Nobilitie of Fraunce committed in the towne of Pariſe, on ſainct Barthelmewes daye, in the yere 1572. how poore priſonners and perſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes erreſted in forme of lawe, within the concergeries of the Palace of Pariſe aforeſayd, of Tolouſe, Bordeaux, Roane, Lyon, and Orleans, and other Townes haue been burned, ſlayne and murdered, beſide an infinitie number of perſones of good eſtate, women, children, and other citezens of the ſayde townes, and alſo their goods rauenouſly ſpoiled by theſe that are at this day honored, fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and auaunced.</p>
            <p>How the King and his Realme are ſtill poſſeſſed, as they haue been in the time of the late Kinges his brethren, by ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers whiche haue conſpired to the totall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of his Maieſtie, the Princes of his blood, and his Nobilitie, as they haue ſufficiently made appeare by putting them to the aſſaultes of townes, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates,
<pb facs="tcp:26953:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 65 -->
and other haſardes at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to the intent vtterly to deface the memorie and wholy to vſurpe the eſtate and crowne of Fraunce.</p>
            <p>How ſince the deceſſe of the good King Henrie, the Nobilitie hath been wholly defaced in France, and their merites and vertues deſpiſed: how ſtraungers haue ben preferred before them to the charges and eſtates of the Crowne, and of the Kinges houſehold, againſt the auncient lawes of the eſtabliſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of this Realm. Yea and whiche more is, the ſaid eſtates haue ben geuen to ſome that be no ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, nor haue ſhewed ſo muche, as any ſmall profe of any thing nere to any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing of ſuche charge. Wherof enſueth an extreme grefe to an infinite number of old Knightes and Capitaines of Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, in reſpecte of the longe ſeruices of their aunceſters, and whiche themſelues haue not ſpared their liues, their goods, their children, their kinred and their frendes, and all that they had, for the ſeruice of the King, and for the maintenaunce of his eſtate. So as brefely the countrey of the
<pb facs="tcp:26953:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 65 -->
worlde that moſte plentuouſly furniſhed good examples to all other, is now ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered and defiled, that in ſteede of reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering the auncient vertues that in time paſt there abounded in all thinges, now no man can otherwiſe iudge, but that the deſolations and calamities, whiche we haue ſuffred, haue directly proceded from the wrathe of God, wholly powred out vpon the people of Fraunce, by the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion, whiche theſe ſtraungers the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerners of the Eſtate haue brought in, and for lacke of obſeruing the order and the rule, whiche of auncient time haue been ſo well eſtabliſhed, as no prouince was comparable to ours, like as while the policie thereof was inueolably kept, it hath floriſhed and ben renomed aboue all other nations, and ſince the diſorder and ſubuerſion haue ben brought in by theſe newe gouerners with their nouelties, they haue ſought to make the Kinges ſubiectes liue like brute beaſtes, without doctrine, or obſeruing of any thing that they ought, depriuing them of ſuche lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men as were in the Vniuerſities, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by murder, or baniſhement into
<pb facs="tcp:26953:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 66 -->
ſtraunge countreyes, permitting that the Eccleſiaſticall perſones (from whome ought to procede to vs the principall exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples) neither ſtudie, nor preache, nor be reſident, nor exerciſing themſelues in any part of their dutie, that their vnſatiable couetiſe in their pluralitie of benefices hath free courſe than euer it had, that the poore, the needie, and the orphane be wholly forſaken: and all other workes of charitie, are by the ſayd Eccleſiaſticall perſones wholly reiected and eloigned: how thei let out their benefices to ferme, not caryng to whom, and by the ſame meane dooe in their abſence leaue the charge of their owne ſoules, and of their flocke as it were to fermers and tenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: and chefly how the elections ordeined by the holy Counſelles, and confirmed by the ſayd ordinances of Orleans, haue ben repelled and reuoked for the priuate pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of ſtrangers, whiche haue ben, and be ſuche as hardly they might be capable to be called by the people of Fraunce, to any charges and dignities ſpirituall or tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26953:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 66 -->How ſince that iuſtice is adminiſtred for money, and that there hath ben ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred in Fraunce againſt our lawes, that the preſident Biragne a Millanois, hath been made Chaunceller of Fraunce, and that all the learned and ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that might haue ben choſen to thoſe charges haue been reiected, we haue had nothing but meſchef in iuſtice, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of all the murders, ſlaughters, and traitorous outrages that haue been executed and conſpired, ſince he hath been in charge: brefely how all his edictes haue tended only to the ſubuerſion of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie and of the crowne of France, both in depriuyng them of the liberties, in erection of offices, and in new tributes and vngracious inuentions that he hath deuiſed with certaine other ſtraungers his miniſters, to praue the ſubſtaunce of Frenchemen, to mainteine (as he hath done hetherto) a diuiſion and confuſion among them, and in the ſame to gather and mainteine armes leuied for the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of his practiſes, by whiche meanes he hath done what in him laye to create a ſtraunger the Kinges Lieutenant ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
<pb facs="tcp:26953:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 67 -->
in his Realme, diſapointing my Lorde his Maieſties brother of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe that was made him by the late King, by occaſion whereof and of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contentmente that my ſayd Lord gaue, to wite, that he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiued thereby, he is at this day as captiue, &amp; all thoſe that were thought affectioned to the ſeruice of the King, and to mainteine that which iuſtly belonged vnto him, and to my ſayd Lorde his brother, or whiche haue bent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt this tyrannie, oppreſſion, and euell counſell, as well Princes of the blood, &amp; officers of his Maieſties crowne, as other, haue been put to death, exiled, or be deteined priſoners.</p>
            <p>Hauing be on all that they were able, vnder falſe and ſclanderous perſuaſions, in the ſame time of the others empri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonemente, they haue practiſed to cauſe vs to be ſlayne by the Counte Martin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nengues, and diuerſe other expreſly ſent to this towne of Montpellier to make vs to be priſoned, or to be murdered in a tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multe of the people (a thing ſo commonly knowen as euerie man can depoſe it)
<pb facs="tcp:26953:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 67 -->
howbeit this is a particular matter wher with we will not now entermedle, dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling onely with the generall, and refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng this to time and place for vs conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, to debate this cauſe and all the reſt concerning vs, and to make it knowen to his Maieſtie that without iuſt occaſion, this miſcheuous treaſon and conſpiracie hath been attempted.</p>
            <p>Now we hauing lately iorneyed into Piedmont, to his Maieſties preſence (by his commaundement, at ſuche tyme as he returned fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Poloigne into his owne Realme) to vnderſtand his good pleaſure, and to geue him aduiſe, as he required vs by writing from Venize, of the meanes that then were to appeaſe the troubles of his Realme, accordyng to his inclination to ſo good intent by hymſelf ſufficiently publiſhed, and made knowen to his ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes, &amp; to Princes and Potentates ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and his allies, his Maieſtie had di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe tymes doen vs ſo greate honour, to aſſure vs of this his ſo ſincere and lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble intention, to enter with peace, and to embrace the vnitie of his ſayd ſubiectes
<pb facs="tcp:26953:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 68 -->
of bothe Religions, to make them parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the benefite and quietneſſe that he meant to them, in ſuche ſorte that we loked for nothing, but this vniuerſall good at our returne from the towne of Suze to this our gouernement, there to attend (as his Maieſtie had expreſly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded vs for theſe, whome it ſhoulde pleaſe him to ſend to aſſiſt vs, &amp; to ſeke the meanes of the ſayd pacification. But he being ſtill in the power of thoſe that had counſelled the late King, to the oppreſſion and ruine of his Eſtates, hindering the fruite of his good purpoſe, they haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned as they yet dayly do continue, the execution of their practiſes and deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, conſuming wholy the finaunces of France in the entertening of an armie in a maner all of ſtraungers, as Suyſſers, Reiſters, and Piedmontois. One part of whiche armye is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ducted into this coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of Languedoc by the lord d'Vzes, a man knowen among Frenchemen for one that vnder colour of the Religion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, whiche he fained hymſelf to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in times paſt, hath ruined, ſpoiled, and ſacked all the good townes of this
<pb facs="tcp:26953:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 68 -->
cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, defaced and beaten downe all the faire monaſteries, and Churches cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dral and collegiate, and taken and robbed the iewelles that were in them, whiche now fayling him, therewith alſo haue fayled his religion and godlineſſe that he pretended to embraſe, and alſo the cruel and miſerable death of the lord of Bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nay his brother: and he hath accepted this charge to the intent to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue with theſe oppreſſers and diſturbers of France the ruine thereof.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, into Prouence is conducted a part of the ſayd armye by the Mareſchal of Gondy, a ſtraunger to this Realme, to whome this charge (as it is eaſy to perceiue) hath been committed for the diſtruſt that hath been had of thoſe of that contreye, whiche wolde be executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of ſo miſcheuous purpoſes for the ſubuerſion of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Wherupon hauyng been made to vs ſondry declarations and exhortations, as well on the behalf of the Princes of the blood, officers of the Crowne, and Pairs
<pb facs="tcp:26953:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 69 -->
of Fraunce, as alſo of all the prouinces of this Realme, whiche know the immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent deſtruction of the King and of his eſtate at ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, if neceſſarie remedie thereto be not ſpedily prouided. We as an offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of the Crowne, a naturall Frenche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and deſcended of the firſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and barons of Fraunce, whiche from time beyond all memorie haue had before their eyes in ſingular recomman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation the protection, preſeruation, and defenſe of their Kinges &amp; their Crownes, whiche we deſire by the helpe of God, to follow in all that we poſſibly may:</p>
            <p>Hauing well conſidered that the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie which is in this Realm for matter of Religion, neither can nor ought to be determined by armes, but by a holy and free cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell general or national, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that it is moſt requiſite that there be an eſtabliſhment of all things in their firſt eſtate, by the aduiſe and deliberation of an aſſemblie of the ſtates generall, the onely remedie to appeaſe troubles, and the only piller and vpholding of the King and of his Crowne, whatſoeuer the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantes,
<pb facs="tcp:26953:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 69 -->
flatterers, and clokers of truthe can ſay to the contrarie.</p>
            <p>We hauing an extreme greef to ſee his Maieſtie poſſeſſed, by perſones that haue ſo ſmall regard vnto him, that they publikely abuſe his ſacred name, to couer their vngratious intention, vnſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe and ambition, Haue embraſed the common protection, preſeruation and defenſe of the Crowne, and of the ſayd good and naturall ſubiectes, as well of the one Religion as of the other, of what qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie or condition ſoeuer they be, againſt the ſayd ſtraungers, euell counſells, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſers and violaters of the vnitie and common quiet of this ſayd Realme, and of the libertie of my Lord the Kinges bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the King of Nauarre, my Lord the prince of Conde, and other Princes of the blood, officers of the Crowne, Lordes, Gentlemen, and other Capitaines pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners and exiled, as is aforeſayd.</p>
            <p>Calling to our ſuccor and ayde all Kinges Princes, and Potentates of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, frendes and confederates of this
<pb facs="tcp:26953:8"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 70 -->
Crowne, and all the faithfull ſubiectes of the ſame, hoping that God will geue vs the grace by armes to come to a good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of Religion, to the vnitie and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of this Realme in the former eſtate, by the determination of a holy and free counſell generall or nationall, and by the deliberation and aduiſe of the general aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie of the eſtates of Fraunce.</p>
            <p>We notifie to all the ſayd ſubiectes of his Maieſtie, of what eſtate, condition or qualitie ſoeuer they be, to all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, Townes, and Commonalties of this Realme, that will fauor, ayde, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt vs in this ſo good, ſo iuſt, and ſo ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous enterpriſe, for the publike weale of his ſayd Maieſtie, and of all his Realme, that they ſhalbe pre ſerued, maintened, and kept in all liberties of their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, exerciſe of their Religion, as well Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiks as Reformed, according as ſhalbe particularly aduiſed at this next aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie general, by vs aſſigned in this towne of Montpellier, and in the full and free enioyyng of their dignities, eſtates, goods fruites, reuenues, and profites, as well
<pb facs="tcp:26953:8"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 70 -->
Eccleſiaſtical as other, without exception of any whatſoeuer, and from this time as alſo from thenceforthe wee haue taken and do take and admit them vnder the Kinges and our protection and ſafegard. As alſo we declare that they whiche ſhall ſhew themſelues contrarie to vs, and our commaundementes to the purpoſe aboue ſayd, ſhalbe runne vpon as enimies of the eſtate and crowne of Fraunce, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbers of the vnitie and common peace.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>At Montpellier <date>1575.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>The blood of our brethren crieth out of the earth.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
